Guide to the Franz R. and Kathryn M. Stenzel Research Files on Western American Art
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Personal Papers, [1910]-1982; Series VIII; 1.68; (4 boxes)
  - ART COLLECTION PAPERS
    - Photographs
      - Copy photographs of miscellaneous pieces of art, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1542)
    - Printed Material
      - About Franz Stenzel
        - Clippings about Franz Stenzel, 1959-73 (Box 55, Folder 1543-1544)
          Includes clippings about Swan and
          Paxson exhibitions
        - Life magazine with photograph of Stenzel performing art restoration, 1959 Apr 13
      - By Franz Stenzel
        - A Catalogue. Art of the Oregon Territory. Paintings from the Collection of Dr. and Mrs. Franz Stenzel. Eugene, Oregon: Museum of Art, University of Oregon, 1959 (Box 55, Folder 1545)
        - Anton Schonborn Western Forts. Fort Worth: Amon Carter Museum, 1972 (Box 55, Folder 1546)
        - An Art Perspective of the Historic Pacific Northwest. From the Collection of Dr. and Mrs. Franz R. Stenzel, Portland, Oregon. Exhibited at Montana Historical Society, August, 1963. Eastern Washington State Historical Society, September, 1963 (Box 55, Folder 1547)
          Accompanied by a page from The
          Arthur H. Clark Co. advertising An Art Perspective for sale
        - Early Days in the Northwest. Portland, Oregon: Portland Art Museum, 1959 (Box 55, Folder 1548)
          Priced for insurance
        - Fragments from exhibition catalogs, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1549)
      - Other Printed Material
        - Stenzel Christmas cards reproducing art in their collection, 1974, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1550-1551)
          Artists: Alfred Agate, Alden,
          Charles Brinton Cox, George M.
          Ottinger, Paxson, William Tylee
          Ranney, Cleveland Rockwell, John
          Mix Stanley, James Everett Stuart
        - "Matching Masters." Exhibition at the Portland Art Museum, 1965 (Box 55, Folder 1552)
    - Other Papers
      - Scrapbook of memorabilia relating to the Stenzel art collection and related activity, 1959-72, n.d.
        Stored in: Oversize box 59, folder
        1610
      - Scrapbook of artists and images owned by the Stenzels. 2 leaves completed, rest of scrapbook blank, with clippings about the Stenzels' collection and publicity photographs laid in loose, 1961-73
        All materials removed from scrapbook
        and retained; empty scrapbook
        discarded per curator (7/02).
      - Laminated sign advertising Sotheby Parke Bernet sale with artwork owned by Stenzel featured, [1980]
        Stored in: Oversize, box 57, folder
        1598
      - Interview: Franz Stenzel on Public Television. 16mm motion picture (VHS reference copy has been made), [ca. 1965]
      - Label "Columbia River 1852" from unidentified piece of art, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1553)
      - Invitations, printed material and other papers related to The American West Exhibition by the Amon Carter Museum for the United States Information Agency, 1974 (Box 55, Folder 1554)
  - PERSONAL PAPERS
    - Printed Material
      - Programs for and invitations to Stenzel presentations, 1963-75 (Box 56, Folder 1555)
      - Occidental Life mailing introducing Franz Stenzel, Jr., n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1556)
      - Miscellaneous clippings, 1972-73, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1557)
    - Photographs
      - Publicity photographs of Franz and Kathy Stenzel, 1955-72, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1558)
      - Photographs of the Stenzels and friends, 1972-73, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1559)
      - Photographs of Franz Stenzel and Vincent Price at a museum exhibition, 1959 (Box 56, Folder 1560)
      - Photograph of Vincent Price, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1561)
      - Photograph of the Amon Carter Museum, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1562)
      - Photographs of exhibit of Native American clothes, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1562a)
      - Photographs of automobiles made by the Stevens-Duryea Company of Chicopee, Mass. and Knox Automobile Company of Springfield, Mass., [ca. 1910] (Box 56, Folder 1563)
    - Other Papers
      - Architect's floor plan of a house for Dr. and Mrs. Stenzel, Geo. K. Butler, architect
      - Franz Stenzel's birth certificates, diplomas, and hospital appointments. Photographic copies, [1946] (Box 56, Folder 1564)
      - Contract to lecture at Oregon State University, 1976 May 18 (Box 56, Folder 1565)
      - Receipts and ticket stubs, 1964-82 (Box 56, Folder 1566)
      - List of boats and crews in Capitol to Capitol Race, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 1567)
      - Notes on piloting, seamanship and electronics, 1968, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1568-1569)
      - Miscellaneous notes by Stenzel, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1570)
- Oversize, 4.94; (4 boxes)
  Oversize contains material from Series I, II, V, VI,
  and VIII and is listed in box order.
  - Genealogical chart of the John Alden family (in Series I), n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1571)
  - Ruth Dixon Correspondence (in Series II) (Box 57, Folder 1572)
  - Margaret Ellis Correspondence (in Series II) (Box 57, Folder 1573)
  - Franz Stenzel's notes on Swan (in Series II), n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1574)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Brewerton, George Douglas (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1575)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Collins, Caspar W. - Colman, Samuel (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1576)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Engel - Evans (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1577)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Gass - Gay (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1578)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Gifford, Sanford Robinson (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1579)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Griset, Ernest Henry (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1580)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Grob - Gustin (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1581)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Howe, Henry - Howland, John Dare (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1582)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Inchbold - Isaacs (in Series V), 1962 (Box 57, Folder 1583)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Johnson, George Cady - Juke (in Series I) (Box 57, Folder 1584)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Lindsay - Lofgren (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1585)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Masterson - Matthews (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1586)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Meyers - Mills (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1587)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Moellman - Moore (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1588)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Ranney, William Tylee (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1589)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Ravalli - Reinhart (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1590)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Russell, Charles (in Series V), 1970 (Box 57, Folder 1591)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Schroff - Selander (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1592)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Sully, Alfred (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1593)
  - Artist Information Index, Oregon Sculpture File, Proctor, Phimister (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1594)
  - Artist Information Index, "Not Northwest" File, Aaris - Amick (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1595)
  - Artist Information Index, "Not Northwest" File, Anderson - Austin (in Series V) (Box 57, Folder 1596)
  - Life magazine with photograph of Stenzel performing art restoration (in Series VIII), 1959 Apr 13 (Box 57, Folder 1597)
  - Laminated sign advertising Sotheby Parke Bernet sale with artwork owned by Stenzel featured (in Series VIII), [1980] (Box 57, Folder 1598)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Beard - Beil (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1599)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Bigelow - Blakelock (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1600)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Borglum, Gutzon (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1601)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Borglum, Solon (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1602)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Dixon - Downing (in Series V), 1948, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 1603)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Gale - Garrigan (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1604)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Gifford, Robert Swain (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1605)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Ottinger - Palenske (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1606)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Paxson, E. S. (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1607)
  - Artist Information Index, Main File, Schofield - Schoonover (in Series V) (Box 58, Folder 1608)
  - Artist Information Index, Alberta File, Tempest - Winter (in Series V), 1976 (Box 58, Folder 1609)
  - Scrapbook of memorabilia relating to the Stenzels' art collection and related activity (in Series VIII), 1959-72, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1610)
  - Scrapbook of artists and images owned by the Stenzels. 2 leaves completed, rest of scrapbook blank, with clippings about the Stenzels' collection and publicity photographs laid in loose (in Series VIII), 1961-73 (Box 60, Folder 1611)
  - Interview: Franz Stenzel on Public Television. 16mm motion picture, [ca. 1965] (Box 60a, Folder 1611a)
    VHS Reference copy available.
  - McMurtrie, William B. "Reconnaissance of the Western Coast of the United States [Lower Sheet] San Francisco to San Diego." Engraving (in Series I), 1853 (Box bsd, Folder 1612)
  - McMurtrie, William B. "Reconnaissance of the Western Coast of the United States. Middle Sheet From San Francisco to Umpquah River." Engraving (in Series I), 1854
    In same folder as map above
  - McMurtrie, William B. "Reconnaissance of the Western Coast of the United States [Northern Sheet] From Umpquah River to the Boundary." Engraving (in Series I), 1855
    In same folder as maps above
  - U.S. Coast Survey maps of Washington and Oregon. Hydrography by the Party under the Command of Lieut. James Alden U.S.N. Assistant. 11 maps (in Series I), 1853-54 (Box bsd, folder 1613)
  - Gibbs, George and Edmund A. Starling. "Sketch of the Willamette Valley, showing the purchases and reservations made by the Board of Commissioners appointed to treat with the Indians of Oregon April and May, 1831." Copy (in Series VI) (Box bsd, folder 1614)
  - Parks, George A. Early Exploratory Routes Alaska. Copy (in Series VI) (Box bsd, folder 1615)
  - Stansbury, M. H. Map of the United States Territory of Oregon West of the Rocky Mountains. Washington, 1838. Copy (in Series VI), n.d. (Box bsd, folder 1616)
  - Architect's floor plan of a house for Dr. and Mrs. Stenzel, Geo. K. Butler, architect (in Series VIII) (Box bsd, folder 1617)
  - Empty folder (Box bsd, Folder 1618)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 2.81; (6 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folders 4, 38 (Box 61, Folder 1619)
  - Box 2, folders 71, 80, 85-86, 89 (Box 61, Folder 1620)
  - Box 4, folders 100-103 (Box 61, Folder 1621)
  - Box 5, folder 126 (Box 61, Folder 1622)
  - Box 6, folders 133, 137, 139-141 (Box 61, Folder 1623)
  - Box 7, folder 160 (Box 61, Folder 1624)
  - Box 8, folders 171, 183-185, 190 (Box 61, Folder 1625)
  - Box 9, folders 191-194 (Box 61, Folder 1626)
  - Box 10, folder 206 (Box 61, Folder 1627)
  - Box 11, folders 216, 235, 243, 257, 267 (Box 61, Folder 1628)
  - Box 12, folders 271-272, 275, 280-281 (Box 61, Folder 1629)
  - Box 13, folders 284, 286-298 (Box 61, Folder 1630)
  - Box 14, folders 299-311, 313-314 (Box 61, Folder 1631)
  - Box 15, folders 316-329 (Box 61, Folder 1632)
  - Box 16, folders 330-336 (Box 61, Folder 1633)
  - Box 16, folders 337-345 (Box 61, Folder 1634)
  - Box 17, folders 346-347, 349-354 (Box 61, Folder 1635)
  - Box 17, folders 355-361 (Box 62, Folder 1636)
  - Box 18, folders 362-369 (Box 62, Folder 1637)
  - Box 18, folders 370-376 (Box 62, Folder 1638)
  - Box 19, folders 377-386 (Box 62, Folder 1639)
  - Box 19, folders 387-390 (Box 62, Folder 1640)
  - Box 20, folders 391-395, 397-399 (Box 62, Folder 1641)
  - Box 20, folders 400-403 (Box 62, Folder 1642)
  - Box 21, folders 406-407, 409-412 (Box 62, Folder 1643)
  - Box 21, folders 414-416, 419 (Box 62, Folder 1644)
  - Box 22, folders 421, 423-428 (Box 63, Folder 1645)
  - Box 22, folders 429-434 (Box 63, Folder 1646)
  - Box 23, folders 435-439 (Box 63, Folder 1647)
  - Box 23, folders 440-441, 443-448 (Box 63, Folder 1648)
  - Box 24, folders 449-454 (Box 63, Folder 1649)
  - Box 24, folders 455-462 (Box 63, Folder 1650)
  - Box 25, folders 463-469 (Box 63, Folder 1651)
  - Box 25, folders 470-479 (Box 63, Folder 1652)
  - Box 26, folders 481-483, 486-491 (Box 63, Folder 1653)
  - Box 26, folders 492-493, 495-497 (Box 63, Folder 1654)
  - Box 27, folders 499, 501-502, 504-507 (Box 64, Folder 1655)
  - Box 27, folders 508-514 (Box 64, Folder 1656)
  - Box 28, folders 515-520, 522 (Box 64, Folder 1657)
  - Box 28, folders 523-530 (Box 64, Folder 1658)
  - Box 29, folders 531-536, 541-543 (Box 64, Folder 1659)
  - Box 30, folders 545-547, 549-550, 553, 556-558 (Box 64, Folder 1660)
  - Box 31, folders 559, 562-564, 566, 568, 571 (Box 64, Folder 1661)
  - Box 32, folders 573-574, 576-579 (Box 64, Folder 1662)
  - Box 32, folders 580, 582-583, 585 (Box 64, Folder 1663)
  - Box 33, folders 586-589, 591 (Box 64, Folder 1664)
  - Box 34, folders 613-616 (Box 64, Folder 1665)
  - Box 35, folders 619-623 (Box 64, Folder 1666)
  - Box 36, folders 629-630, 632, 634, 638 (Box 64, Folder 1667)
  - Box 37, folders 652-653 (Box 64, Folder 1668)
  - Box 38, folder 674a (Box 64, Folder 1668a)
  - Box 41, folders 801, 810 (Box 64, Folder 1669)
  - Box 42, folders 857-858, 862, 865, 878, 880, 891, 895, 908 (Box 64, Folder 1670)
  - Box 43, folders 933, 941 (Box 64, Folder 1671)
  - Box 44, folder 1031 (Box 64, Folder 1672)
  - Box 45, folder 1094 (Box 64, Folder 1673)
  - Box 46, folder 1143 (Box 64, Folder 1674)
  - Box 49, folders 1334, 1346, 1361 (Box 64, Folder 1675)
  - Box 50, folder 1405 (Box 64, Folder 1676)
  - Box 51, folder 1443 (Box 64, Folder 1677)
  - Box 53, folder 1509, 1512-1514, 1516, 1520-1521, 1525 (Box 64, Folder 1678)
  - Box 54, folder 1528 (Box 64, Folder 1679)
  - Box 55, folder 1543-1544 (Box 65, Folder 1680)
  - Box 56, folder 1557 (Box 65, Folder 1681)
  - Box 60, folder 1611 (Box 65, Folder 1682)
  - Box 8, folder 18 (Box 66, Folder 1683)
  - Box 10, folder 206 (Box 66, Folder 1684)
  - Box 22, folder 427 (Box 66, Folder 1685)
  - Box 54, folders 1531-1535 (Box 67 (Cold storage), Folder 1686)
  - Box 60a, folder 1611a (Box 1687 (Cold storage))